Guide to the Brown Brothers Harriman Records 1696-1973, 1995 (bulk, 1820-1968) MS 78
New-York Historical Society
Brown Brothers Harriman records
1696-1973, 1995 (bulk, 1820-1968)
New-York Historical Society
Kouwenhoven, John Atlee, 1909-1990
Brown Brothers, Harriman & Co.
Brown, Shipley & Co.
MS 78
109 Linear feet (148 boxes, 212 volumes)
The Records consist of original and secondary research materials amassed to support the writing of Partners in Banking for the 150th anniversary of Brown Brothers Harriman and its predecessor businesses; original records from these entities, including correspondence, ledgers, account books, business transaction records, diaries, daybooks, clippings, scrapbooks, prints, photographs, audio tapes, artifacts; and a research library of printed material.
Access Restrictions
This collection is stored offsite. For information on making arrangements to consult it, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated to the New-York Historical Society in 1970; some materials were added up to 1975.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in ten series:
Series I. Historical Files
Series II. Annual Reports and Statements of Condition
Series III. Financial and Business Records
Series IV. Business Transaction Records
Series V. Partners' Papers
Series VI. Scrapbooks and Collected Material
Series VII. Promotional and Press Material
Series VIII. Visual Material and Audio Tapes
Series IX. Artifacts and Memorabilia
Series X. Published Material
Series I represents the arrangement provided by Kouwenhoven, Brown and Hoban, The remaining series were designated based on the physical and intellectual groupings of the materials.
Historical Note
Belfast linen merchant Alexander Brown emigrated to the United States in 1800 and in 1818 founded Alex. Brown & Sons to import and export commodities, including Irish linen and American tobacco and cotton. The firm later established offices in New York, Boston, and Philadelphia. In 1810, Alexander's eldest son William returned to England and established the trading firm William Brown & Co. in Liverpool. This became Brown Shipley & Co. in 1839 and relocated to London. It separated from Brown Brothers as a distinct business entity in 1918. The extending of credit and other banking-related opportunities that stemmed from international trade gradually became more profitable than the physical moving and sale of actual goods, and these solely financial endeavors became and remained the firm's focus. It originated travelers' letters of credits, later known as travelers checks, which allowed both individuals and corporations to access credit worldwide, through a network of international correspondent banks.
As financing opportunities and cash availability were diminished by the Depression, in 1931 Brown Brothers merged with the Harriman interests, to become Brown Brothers Harriman. The Harriman ventures included widespread investment and other financial holdings organized from Edward R. Harriman's vast fortunes, gained initially through successive mergers into what became the Union Pacific Railroad, and later by extensive and prudent investment.
In 1964 John A. Kouwenhoven, professor of English at Barnard College and the author of The Columbia Historical Portrait of New York, among other works, was hired by Brown Brothers Harriman to identify and amass records of historical value to the firm. His title was Director of the Historical Files, which were to serve, among other purposes, as the research materials for the writing of Partners in Banking, commissioned by Doubleday & Co. publishers to celebrate the firm's 150th anniversary in 1968. Kouwenhoven was assisted by researcher Sarah B. Brown, a former history teacher at the Brearley School and wife of partner Thatcher M. Brown III; and by Patricia Hoban. Mr. and Mrs. Brown were both direct descendants of Brown Brothers founder, Alexander Brown.
Related Materials in Other Collections
The Library of Congress holds records of Alex Brown & Sons from 1796 to 1884, and the papers of W. Averell Harriman.
The New York Public Library's Manuscripts and Archives Division holds 176 volumes of ledgers and other account books from Brown Brothers & Co. in the period 1825-1889. It also holds correspondence of John Crosby Brown, Mary E. Brown, and William Adams Brown in the Brown Gilman Family Papers (1862-1937).
Union Theological Seminary holds the William Adams Brown papers (1865-1938) and the John Crosby Brown papers (1876-1909).
Correspondence related to the appointment of partner Charles J. Rhoads as Commissioner of Indian Affairs in 1929 was donated in March, 1965, as a gift of Brown Brothers Harriman from Mrs. Thatcher M. (Sarah B.) Brown III to the American Philosophical Society, where it is processed as the Charles James Rhoads Papers, 1883-1929.
The Walker Evans Archive at the Metropolitan Museum of Art includes negatives, annotated contact sheets, correspondence, and project ephemera relating to photographs commissioned for Partners in Banking.
At Boston University, the Howard Gotlieb Archival Research Center's nursing collections include records of Mary Magoun Brown (see Subseries V.C.i.).
The Avery Architectural and Fine Arts Library of Columbia University holds a scrapbook of William Adams Delano.
Yale University Library's Division of Manuscripts and Archives holds the personal papers of Robert A. Lovett. Official papers from his government service are housed at the National Archives.
Related Materials at the New-York Historical Society
Materials in the Records were used as research for volumes including John Crosby Brown's 100 Years of Merchant Banking, Thatcher Magoun Brown's Brown Brothers & Co. [and] Brown Brothers Harriman & Co., 1900-1950, Mary Elizabeth Brown's St. Cloud Church, and John A. Kouwenhoven's Partners in Banking, all of which are in the Society's library collection.
Some letters from John Crosby Brown related to the sermons and papers of his maternal grandfather, Rev. Jonas Coe, are included in the Coe-Brown Family Papers.
The Print Room holds some architectural records of buildings designed by Brown family cousin William Adams Delano and an album of photographs (Album 109) from the 150th anniversary celebrations in Seattle and Sun Valley Idaho in 1968 and given to Juan Trippe.
Sources
Brown, John Crosby: A hundred years of merchant banking. New York, 1909.
Brown, Mary Elizabeth: Alexander Brown and his descendants, 1764-1916. Privately printed, 1917.
Brown, Thatcher M. Brown Brothers & Co. [and] Brown Brothers Harriman & Co., 1900-1950
Kouwenhoven, John A. Partners in banking. New York: Doubleday, 1958.
Descendants of William Brown: http://familytreemaker.genealogy.com/users/b/r/o/George-S-Brown/index.html [accessed December 11, 2009]
James Crosby Brown's Clifton Wynyates. In The First 300: The Amazing and Rich History of Lower Merion (Part 29). http://www.lowermerionhistory.org/texts/first300/part29.html [accessed January 2010]
Scope and Contents
The Records consist of an artificial collection of relevant original and secondary material collected in part to support the publication of Partners in Banking as well as some of the naturally occurring records of Brown Brothers Harriman and its predecessor companies' business activities, and some of those companies' partners. These include original, photocopied, and transcribed correspondence; ledgers and account books; records of international business transactions; daybooks, correspondence, and diaries of Brown Brothers' partners, both personal and professional; scrapbooks; newspaper and magazine clippings, and other publicity materials; prints, photographs, and other visual materials including a portfolio commissioned from photographer Walker Evans; audiotapes; artifacts; and a reference library of published and privately printed material about the Brown family, its business interests, and other background information.
The collection documents the activities of Brown family businesses including Alex. Brown & Co., Brown Brothers & Co., Brown Shipley & Co., and their merger with the Harriman interests in 1931 to form Brown Brothers Harriman. To a lesser extent, it includes information on the Harriman interests, including Union Pacific Railroad.
Academic addresses (documents); Account books.; Annual reports.; Audiotapes; Bills of exchange.; Black-and-white negatives; Botanical specimens; Building plans.; Catalogs (documents); Certificates.; Checkbooks; Checks (bank checks); Clippings (information artifacts); Color negatives.; Color slides.; Contact prints.; Contracts.; Correspondence.; Deeds.; Diaries.; Drafts (negotiable instruments); Engravings (prints); Ephemera.; Financial records.; Flags.; Greeting cards; House organs; Inventories; Invitations.; Leases.; Ledgers (account books); Legal instruments; Letterpress copies; Letters of credit.; Manuscripts (documents); Medals.; Newspapers.; Photocopies.; Photographic prints.; Photoreproductions; Plaques; Reports.; Scrapbooks.; Slides (photographs).; Snapshots; Speeches (documents); Stereographs.; Stock certificates.; Tax returns; Tear sheets.; Telegrams.; Transcripts.; Typescripts.; Banks and banking -- Great Britain -- History.; Banks and banking -- Maryland -- Baltimore.; Banks and banking -- New York (State) -- New York.; Banks and banking -- United States -- History.; Cold War; Commerce -- Periodicals.; Commercial credit; Cotton trade; Economic assistance, American -- Latin America.; Debt, Public; Depressions -- 1907 -- United States.; Economic assistance, American -- Europe.; Finance -- United States -- History.; Financial crises -- United States.; Financial services industry; Insurance; International finance; International finance -- History -- 20th century.; Investment banking; Linen industry -- Northern Ireland -- History.; Marshall Plan; Memorials (Commemorative) -- 20th century.; Merchants -- England -- Liverpool -- History -- 19th century.; Money.; Money -- United States.; Municipal bonds; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Reconstruction (1939-1951) -- Europe.; Securities; Securities industry -- United States -- History.; Shipping -- United States.; Sinking-funds; Steam-navigation -- United States -- History.; Syndicates (Finance); Wages; World War, 1914-1918 -- Finance; World War, 1939-1945 -- Finance; Arden House (Harriman, N.Y.); Baltimore (Md.); Dukes County (Mass.) -- History.; East Orange (N.J.) -- Church history.; Liverpool (England) -- Commerce.; Lower Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Martha's Vineyard (Mass.) -- History.; New Orleans (La.); New York (N.Y.); New York (N.Y.) -- Politics and government.; Nicaragua -- History -- 1838-1909.; Nicaragua -- History -- 1909-1937.; Nicaragua -- Relations -- United States.; Orange (N.J.) -- History.; Russia -- Economic conditions.; Russia -- History -- 1801-1917.; Seattle (Wash.); Seattle (Wash.) -- Pictorial works.; United States -- Economic policy.; United States -- Economic policy -- To 1933; United States -- Foreign economic relations -- 20th century.; United States -- Foreign relations -- 20th century.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States -- Commerce -- Directories.; United States -- Foreign relations -- 1945-1989.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1989-.; United States -- Relations -- Nicaragua.; Wall Street (New York, N.Y.); Capitalists and financiers; Adams, William, 1807-1880; Barry, Philip, 1896-1949; Brown, Alexander, 1764-1834; Brown, Alexander Crosby, 1905-1993; Brown, James, 1863-1943; Brown, John Crosby, 1838-1909; Brown, Mary Elizabeth, 1842-1918; Brown, Thatcher Magoun, 1876-1954; Brown, William, Sir, 1784-1864; Brown, William Adams, 1865-1943; Brown, Winthrop G. (Winthrop Gilman), 1907-1987; Bush, Prescott Sheldon, 1895-1972; Clay, Henry, 1883-1954; Delano, William Adams, 1874-1960; Edwards, Monroe, 1808-1847; Evans, Walker, 1903-1975; Fisk, James, 1835-1872; Forrestal, James, 1892-1949; Harriman, Edward Henry, 1848-1909; Harriman, E. Roland (Edward Roland), 1895-1978; Harriman, Florence Jaffray, 1870-1967; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986; Hunt, Freeman, 1804-1858; Kennan, George F. (George Frost), 1904-2005; King, Moses, 1853-1909; Kouwenhoven, John Atlee, 1909-1990; Lovett, Robert A. (Robert Abercrombie), 1895-1986; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982; Marshall, George C. (George Catlett), 1880-1959; Norman, Montagu, 1871-1950; Parker, Dorothy, 1893-1967; Roosa, Robert V.; Brown family; Harriman family; Magoun (Family); Alex. Brown & Sons -- History; Arctic (Paddle steamship); Baltimore and Ohio Railroad Company -- History; Bangor and Aroostook Railroad Company; Bank for Savings in the City of New York; Bank of England -- History; Brown Brothers & Company; Brown, Shipley & Co.; Collins Line; Columbia-Presbyterian Medical Center; Crosby Brown Collection of Musical Instruments (Metropolitan Museum of Art); Delaware and Hudson Railroad Corporation; Green-Wood Cemetery (New York, N.Y.); Grove Church (New Durham, N.J.) -- History; Madison Avenue Presbyterian Church (New York, N.Y.); New York Stock Exchange; Norfolk and Western Railway Company; St. Cloud Presbyterian Church (East Orange, N.J.) -- History; Union Pacific Railroad Company; Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.); Yale University -- Alumni and alumnae; United States. Department of State; U.S. Mail Steamship Company
- Series I. Historical Files (1699-1974), 1820-1968; 39 Linear feet (81 document boxes, 6 oversize boxes, 12 volumes)
  Scope and Content
  The series includes original, photocopied, and secondary materials consisting of correspondence, photographs, ledgers, account books, clippings, and brochures. They document many aspects of the founding, management, and evolution of Brown Brothers Harriman and its constituent preceding organizations including Brown Brothers & Co., Brown Shipley & Co., and W.A. Harriman & Co., as well as biographical information about partners, staff members, and other relevant individuals. They also include records of all aspects of the preparation, publication, and publicity for Partners in Banking. Because the Files were specifically compiled as research for this book, they form a consciously chosen, or artificial, collection rather than a true archive of the companies' naturally occurring records over time. Material continued to be added to the Historical Files sporadically until 1975.
  As well as documenting the company's history, the Files provide details about the business processes of financial firms over a period of 200 years, including changes in long-distance communications, financial instruments, image creation and distribution, and staffing decisions.
  Because the Historical Files were compiled as an aid to research, they include significant repetition and overlap of materials. For example, Subseries D. Historical Files Director's Files, complements information on the firm's 150th anniversary celebrations also documented in the 1968 files of Subseries A. Chronological Files, and the "150th anniversary" and "Sesquicentennial" files in Subseries B. Subject Files. There is extensive and detailed cross-referencing of documents in Subseries I.A. Chronological, I.B. Subjects, and I.C. People, documented in the "cross-reference sheets" in each of those.
  The photographic prints in this series include those reproduced in Partners in Banking, sometimes with their accompanying negatives. These provide information on sources, permissions, and the images' placement in the book's final layout. Many are not original to the collection but were sourced from other places for use in the book.
  Included with the Records, and available for researchers' use in the Reading Room, is an index to the Historical Files compiled by Kouwenhoven and Brown, in the form of a six-drawer card catalog organized into two sections: one alphabetical and one chronological. Its level of detail and cross-referencing is greater than the container lists below and complements the word-searchable capabilities of this Finding Aid.
  Historical Note
  In compiling the Historical Files, Kouwenhoven and Brown consulted existing published and archival records, visited Brown ancestral properties and company facilities, and interviewed current and past Brown Brothers Harriman partners, managers, and employees. From these many sources they accessioned original material, photocopies, and transcripts to add to the Historical Files based on the information's usefulness to the research and writing of the company's history. Original material was not necessarily preferred over secondary versions.
  Arrangement
  The Historical Files were arranged by Kouwenhoven in three series (Chronological Files, Subject Files, People Files), which form Subseries I.A., I.B., and I.C, respectively. These have been rehoused from their original storage in five three-drawer filing cabinets. Subseries I.D. Historical Files Director's Files contains materials found separately in the Records relating to the formation and running of the Historical Files, including making and answering research requests; and the preparation, publication, and promotion of Partners in Banking.
  The series was originally housed in oversized cardboard folders containing items often in individual folders or envelopes that were heavily annotated on the outside. (Some samples are included at the end of Subseries I.D.) Information available only on the annotations has been photocopied onto acid-free paper and precedes the original item in the files. Users are advised to consult the card catalog in the repository for cross-references to these annotations, since this detailed, item-level information is not reflected in the container list.
  Materials found elsewhere in the collection that were marked for inclusion in the Historical Files but were not yet filed there have been added as appropriate: a notebook of information about guests from Switzerland and the United Kingdom attending the Pacific Northwest 150th anniversary festivities is now included in the "1968" section of the Chronological files (Subseries I.A). Boston office forms, Brown Brothers & Co. correspondence, Tax Department files, and co-partnership records have been added to the Subject files (Subseries I.B.). Clippings about the activities of partner and sometime State Department appointee Robert A. Lovett are now included in the Partners files (Subseries I.C.vi.)
  The dates on folders denote the period for which the material would be relevant to the writing of Partners in Banking, not the date of the material's creation or receipt, which may have been decades or centuries later. For example, information on the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad in 1831 is filed under that date, even though the document itself is dated 1966. Original order has been retained within folders; some materials are now housed in separate oversized (OS) boxes of various sizes, noted in the container lists. Material in the OS boxes is listed here chronologically; there is variation in box numbers within that listing based on the various sizes of oversized materials.
  Volumes 1-12 were originally foldered in the Historical Files; they have been removed and are described together at the end of their respective subseries.
  - Subseries A. Chronological Files (1796-1970), 1818-1968; 31 document boxes, XX OS boxes, 6 volumes
    As well as original and photocopied research materials, the subseries includes cross-reference sheets pointing to relevant information organized elsewhere in Subseries B. Subject Files or Subseries C. People Files, and photographic prints including those used in Partners in Business. The latter sometimes include photographic negatives, and information on sources, permissions, and placement in the book's final layout.
    The files give an overview of the evolution of Brown Brothers from a commodities importation firm to a highly influential worldwide bank and investment house. Important events and topics include agent Joseph Shipley's negotiations with the Bank of England during the panic of 1837; bank actions during the panics of 1857 and 1907 and its contributions to the Gold Fund of 1914; funding actions in Nicaragua from 1911 on, and subsequent investigations of its political consequences; Brown Brothers' relationship and eventual merger with the Harriman interests; changes in partnership agreements and personnel; loans and bond issues; and the firm's interest in and promotion of its history through its anniversary celebrations at 100, 125, and 150 years.
    Materials dating after the 1940s contain more information about the daily administration of the bank, including photographs of current employees and production of the 1959 brochure "Personality of a Bank". Many materials from the mid-1950s appear to have been taken from the scrapbooks of Catherine Barrett (see Series VI. Scrapbooks and Collected Material). From 1964 to 1968 John Kouwenhoven was a Brown Brothers Harriman staff member. The files from that period, including information routinely routed to the Historical Files about the firm's day-to-day operations, policy, and personnel changes, provide a look at business practices of this period. The files also document Kouwenhoven's activities in interviewing current and past employees and partners, and establishing procedures for his office.
    The material in this subseries complements and often duplicates that in the other three subseries of Series I. For example, material on the 150th anniversary celebrations occurs here under "1968" and in the Subject files under both "Sesquicentennial" and "Sun Valley".
    The subseries is arranged chronologically but, within this order, some materials are grouped by subject. These have been inserted at their beginning dates and the chronological order resumes at their completion. They include information on Brown Brothers & Co.'s involvement in Nicaraguan financing, 1911-1929, which follows 1910-1914; the 1914-1918 partner deliberations on separating the business of Brown Shipley & Co. from that of Brown Brothers & Co., which follows 1917; the merger of Brown Brothers & Co. with W.A. Harriman (1928-1935), which follows 1931; the preparation and publication of the brochure "The Personality of a Bank", which follows 1959; funding of Community Research & Development /Rouse Corporation /Columbia MD, which precedes the 1965 files; and the company's 150th anniversary, which follows the other 1968 files.
    Duplication of materials is prevalent. For example, a set of Partners' letterbooks, 1851-1859, was photocopied from microfilm housed at the Liverpool Public Libraries. The 1851-1853 letters were also photocopied, individually foldered, and annotated by Kouwenhoven. These are now arranged by date and each letter is preceded by a photocopy of the annotations.
    Bound volumes 1-6 are listed together at the end of the series, in chronological order.
    Various oversize photographs found organized separately in the Records, but originally marked as belonging to the Chronological files, are included here.